Welcome to this short video on
how to perform intermittent catheterization.
Education and training can help you feel more
confident and enable you to achieve successful catheterization.
You can use this stepbystep video on how
to catheterize with LoFric Origo to support and
follow on from any training given.
Always make sure you follow the advice and
instructions given by your clinician, which is based
on your individual medical and lifestyle needs.
It's quite usual to feel a little anxious and
worried about starting something new for the first time.
Remember that most men who perform
intermittent catheterization find the procedure lifechanging
and easy to perform.
With practice and support, you will soon become
more confident, and intermittent catheterization will become a
natural part of your daily routine.
Start and end the procedure by washing
your hands thoroughly with soap and water.
Hand sanitizer or wet wipes can also be used.
Remember to clean the tip of your penis.
Your clinician can advise you on
a recommended routine for this.
Inside the packaging, there's a sachet with salt solution
you need to squeeze or press to release the
salt solution. The catheter is ready to use.
Pull the tab down to open.
After the package is opened, the
catheter can be taken out.
The packaging has an adhesive tab on the reverse side, which
can be used to attach it to a dry, clean surface.
Position yourself by a toilet and pass any urine, if you're able.
Remove the catheter from the package.
You can pull and adjust the insertion grip to
control insertion without having to touch the catheter tube.
Use your dominant hand to hold the catheter and
use your nondominant hand to hold your penis.
Lift it towards your stomach to straighten
out the urethra and locate the opening.
Slowly and gently insert the
catheter into your urethra.
You may feel some slight resistance as
the catheter reaches your prostate area or
at the sphincter and entrance to your bladder.
If you feel a little tense, find a
good position, cough a little and relax.
Continue gently.
Once urine starts to flow, angle the penis down
and insert the catheter a further 2 to 3 centimeters,
to ensure both eyelids are inside the bladder.
When the urine stops flowing and slows to a drip,
gently and slowly withdraw the catheter a little bit.
If urine starts to flow again, wait until
it is stopped to ensure complete bladder emptying.
Then remove the catheter completely.
The unique LoFric surface coating will ensure
the catheter is still smoothly lubricated.
After you put the catheter back in the
package and dispose appropriately, local regulations may vary.
Your clinician will advise you on
how often to perform intermittent catheterization
based on your individual conditions.
This will, of course, depend on factors such as how
your bladder works, how often you have to catheterize,
how much you drink each day, and other factors.
Remember, LoFric Origo is a urinary catheter
designed to be used only once.
Did you know LoFric Origo can easily
be folded and put in your pocket so
you can take it everywhere you go.
LoFric Origo is ready for you,
whatever your lifestyle needs.
User friendly and safe in a smart package.